Finding Aid for Warner G. Rice papers, 1916-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warner G. Rice papers 1916-1995, 1924-1970
Rice, Warner Grenelle, 1899-
2.5 linear feet
90153 Aa 2
Professor of English at the University of Michigan and director of the University Library; correspondence with colleagues, writings and lectures, organization files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by the estate of Warner Rice (donor no. 2492 ) through William D. Chase, literary executor.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Warner Grenelle Rice was born on July 25, 1899 in Aurora, Illinois. He received a Bachelor of Arts from the University of Illinois in 1920 and a Master of Arts from there in 1922. He was awarded another Master of Arts degree and a doctorate in 1927 from Harvard University where he served as an instructor in English until 1929.
In 1929, Rice began a long association with the University of Michigan with his appointment as associate professor of English. He was promoted to professor in 1936. In 1947, he was named acting chairman and then chairman of the Department of English Language and Literature succeeding Louis Bredvold. In addition to his duties in the English department, he was named Director of the University Library in 1941. He held this position until 1953 when he resigned to concentrate on his duties as department chair and professor of English. He retired from the chair and active teaching in 1968 although he remained interested in the affairs of the university.
Rice's research interests included Milton, biblical illustrations and the commemorative state services added to the Book of Common Prayer of the Church of England in 1662. He served as president of the Milton Society and was a member of the Renaissance Society of America.
After his retirement from the University of Michigan, he served as a consultant to the New York State Education Department from 1969 to 1971. He held visiting professorships at the University of Pittsburgh (1971), Texas Christian University (1971-1972) and Pennsylvania State University (1972-1973).
Warner G. Rice died on January 22, 1997. His wife of 66 years, Mary Wallace Rice died on October 1, 1996. His two daughters live in Evanston, Illinois and San Mateo, California.
This collection includes family correspondence; files pertaining to Historica Critica, organization established to study, record, and celebrate the history of the University of Michigan; honors and awards; correspondence with colleagues and other educational institutions; and writings and lectures. The collection includes materials relating to the Katholepistemiad Club, a University of Michigan faculty club.
Subjects:
Katholepistemiad Club (University of Michigan); Historica Critica.; Rice, Warner Grenelle, 1899-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.
- Family Correspondence 1916-1932
  Family Correspondence (.7 linear ft.) spans the years 1916 to 1932. It contains letters to and from family members or close family friends. The majority of these letters are from Rice's mother.
  - Hortense Macallister (aunt) 1923-1932 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1916-1929, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Fredrick Rice (brother) 1916-1930, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lewis Rice (father) 1916-1926 (Box 1)
  - Louise Grenelle Rice (mother) 1916-1932, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - Norman Rice (brother) 1916-1932, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Stevens "Bud" Rice (brother) 1920-1931 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified 1923-1929 (Box 1)
  - Mary Worst (aunt) 1924-1929 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Worst (cousin) 1924-1928 (Box 1)
- Historica Critica 1985-1987
  Historica Critica (.1 linear ft.) contains largely administrative information about an organization formed to study, record and celebrate the history of the University of Michigan. The series dates from 1985-1987.
  - Administrative 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Agendas 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1985-1987 (Box 1)
- Honors, Awards, and Miscellaneous
  Honors, Awards, and Miscellaneous (.3 linear ft.) spans from 1921-1989 and contains citations, degrees and other honors given to Rice. Some biographical material is included.
  - American Association of University Professors 1989 (Box 2)
  - Biographical Materials 1921-1988 (Box 2)
  - Central Michigan University 1970 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1935-1956 (Box 2)
  - Ninetieth Birthday Celebration
    - Correspondence 1989 (Box 2)
    - Photographs 1989 (Box 2)
  - Wooster College 1953 (Box 2)
- Colleague Correspondence 1922-1995
  Colleague Correspondence (1 linear ft.) covers the years 1922-1995. It contains correspondence with colleagues and associates. Most of the correspondence is personal although there are some official letters which Rice wrote while he was chair of the Department of English Language and Literature.
  - Partial Index undated (Box 2)
  - Bredvold, Louis and Family 1929-1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Bush, Douglas 1926-1983, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Carr, A. J. 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Carson, Gerald and Family 1924-1992, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Downer, James 1989 (Box 2)
  - Ellis, William 1925-1929 (Box 2)
  - Enders, John 1925-1995 (Box 2)
  - Felheim Marvin 1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Fries, Charles and Family 1954-1988 (Box 2)
  - Golder, Harold 1925-1956 (Box 2)
  - Harrison, G.B. 1967-1991 (Box 2)
  - Harwood, Dix 1924-1928 (Box 2)
  - Hornback, Bert 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Litzenberg, Karl 1949-1953 (Box 2)
  - Kuhn, Sherman [1975]-1991 (Box 2)
  - Kato, Sata 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Lames, Hamilton 1927, undated (Box 2)
  - Lowes, John 1927-1929 (Box 2)
  - Marckwardt, Al 1954 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1918-1994 (Box 2)
  - Mullin, Joseph 1977-1991 (Box 2)
  - Nelson, Norman 1955-1984 (Box 2)
  - Ogden, H.V.S. 1958-1988 (Box 2)
  - Orton, Harold 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Patrides, C.A. 1968 (Box 3)
  - Power, Eugene 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Powers, Lyall 1965 (Box 3)
  - Rawoot, Sadashiu 1968-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Rinaker, Clarissa 1922-1929, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Rider, Hazel 1955-1969 (Box 3)
  - Rowe, Kenneth 1953, undated (Box 3)
  - Sands, Donald and Family 1984 (Box 3)
  - Seager, Allan and family 1936-1968 (Box 3)
  - Sontag, Ray 1924-1927 (Box 3)
  - Stader, Karl 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Stevens, A.K. 1956-1963 (Box 3)
  - Steinhoff, William 1954-1992 (Box 3)
  - Stewart, David 1977-1993 (Box 3)
  - Stewart, Rolland 1976-1995, undated (Box 3)
  - Squires, J.R. 1956-1964 (Box 3)
  - Super, Robert 1954-1966 (Box 3)
  - Weaver, Bennett 1953-1970 (Box 3)
  - Wells, Whitney 1925-1927 (Box 3)
- Academic Correspondence 1924-1972
  Academic Correspondence (.1 linear ft.) contains official correspondence between Rice and educational institutions. Included in this series is correspondence from the University of Michigan, Harvard University and Pennsylvania State University. It covers the years from 1924 to 1972.
  - Harvard University 1924-1929 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania State University 1972 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan
    - Administration 1929-1969 (Box 3)
    - Katholepistemiad Club 1897-1979, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Scientific Club 1965-1967 (Box 3)
- Writings and Lectures
  Writings and Lectures (.3 linear ft) consists of handwritten and typed notes made by Rice to assist in his teaching and research. Lectures on Milton's Paradise Lost and research on the Stuart Dynasty in England are prominent in this series.
  - Building for the Future undated (Box 3)
  - English Prayer undated (Box 3)
  - The Function of Poetry undated (Box 3)
  - The King's Evil undated (Box 3)
  - Milton Lectures by WGR undated (Box 3)
  - "Oh Pampina", A Play in Two Acts undated (Box 3)
  - The Stuarts (Kings of England) undated (Box 3)
  - Turk, Moor and Persian in English Literature of the Renaissance
    - Text, 1927, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Photographs, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Writings of WGR undated (Box 3)
Related Material
For further information on Rice's official duties at the university, the researcher is directed to the records of the Department of English Language and Literature and the records of the University Library.